this is lecture three of our class and
we are going to talk today about uh node
embeddings
so the way we think of this is the
following um
what we talked on um last week was about
traditional machine learning in graphs
where the idea was that given an input
graph
we are going to extract some node link
or graph level features
uh that basically describe the
topological structure
of the network either around the node
around a particular link or the entire
graph
and then we can take that topological
information compar
combine it with the attribute based
information
uh to then train a classical machine
learning model like a support vector
machine or a logistic regression
uh to be able to make predictions so um
in this sense right the way we are
thinking of this is that we are given an
input graph here
we are then uh creating structure
structured features or structural
features uh
of this graph so that then we can apply
our learning algorithm and make uh
prediction
and generally most of the effort goes
here into the feature engineering
uh where you know we as uh engineers
human scientists we are trying to figure
out how to best describe
uh this particular network so that uh it
would be most useful
uh for uh downstream prediction tasks um
and uh the question then becomes can we
do this automatically can we kind of get
away from
feature engineering so the idea behind
graph representation learning is that
we wanna alleviate this need to do
manual feature engineering
every single time every time for every
different task
and we want to kind of automatically
learn the
features the structure of the network um
in
that we are interested in and this is
what is called uh representation
learning so that
no manual feature engineering is
necessary
anymore so the idea will be to do
efficient
task independent feature learning for
machine learning with graphs
the idea is that for example if we are
doing this at the level of
individual nodes that for every node we
want to learn
how to map this node in a d-dimensional
space
and represent it as a vector of d
numbers and we will call this
vector of the numbers as feature
representation
or we will call it um unembedding and
the goal will be that this
uh mapping um it happens automatically
and that this vector
captures the structure of the underlying
network that
we are interested in uh analyzing or
making predictions over
so why would you want to do this why
create this embeddings
right the task is to map nodes into an
into an embedding space
um and the idea is that similarity of
the embeddings between nodes
indicates their similarity in the
network
for example you know if both nodes are
close to each other in the network
perhaps they should be embedded close
together in the embedding space
um and the goal of this is that kind of
automatically encodes
the network uh structure information um
and then
you know it can be used for many kinds
of different
downstream prediction tasks for example
you can do any kind of node
classification link prediction
graph classification you can do anomaly
detection you can do clustering
a lot of different things so to give you
an example
uh here is here is a plot from a paper
that came up with this idea back in 2014
2015 the method is called deepwalk
um and they take this small uh small
network that you see here
and then they show how the embedding of
nodes would look like in two dimensions
and
and here the nodes are colored by
different colors
uh they have different numbers and here
in the um
in this example uh you can also see how
um how different nodes get mapped into
different parts of the embedding space
for example all these light blue nodes
end up here
the violet nodes uh from this part of
the network end up here
you know the green nodes are here the
bottom two nodes here get kind of set
uh on a different pa on in a different
place
and basically what you see is that in
some sense this visualization of the
network and the underlying comparing
correspond to each other quite well in
two-dimensional space and of course this
is a small network it's a small
kind of toy toy network but you can get
an idea about
uh how this would look like in uh uh in
more interesting larger uh in larger
dimensions
so that's basically the uh that's
basically the uh idea
so what i wanna now do is to tell you
about how do we formulate this as a task
uh how do we view it in this encoder
decoder
view or definition and then what kind of
practical methods
um exist there for us to be able uh to
do this
so the way we are going to do this um is
that we are going to represent
a graph as a as a with an adjacency
matrix um
and we are going to think of this um in
terms of its adjacency matrix and we are
not going
to assume any feature uh represent
features or
attributes on the nodes of the network
so
we are just going to to think of this as
a as a
as a set of um as an adjacency matrix
that we wanna that we wanna analyze
um we are going to have a graph as i
show it here and the corresponding
adjacency matrix a
and for simplicity we are going to think
of this as undirected graphs
so the goal is to encode nodes so that
similarity in the embedding space
uh similarity and the embedding space
you can think of it as distance
or as a dot product as an inner product
of the coordinates of two nodes
approximates the similarity in the graph
space right so the idea will be that
in the in the original network i want to
take the notes i want to map them
into the embedding space i'm going to
use the letter z
to denote the coordinates uh of that of
that embedding
of a given node um and the idea is that
you know
some notion of similarity here
corresponds to some notion of similarity
in the embedding space and the goal is
to learn this encoder
that encodes the original network as a
set of
node embeddings so the goal is to
to define the similarity in the original
network
um and to map nodes into the coordinates
in the embedding space
such that uh similarity of their
embeddings corresponds to their
similarity in the network uh and as a
similarity metric in the embedding space
uh people usually uh select um
dot product and dot product is simply
the angle
uh between the two vectors right so when
you do the dot product it's the cosine
of the
of the angle so if the two points are
close together or
in the same direction from the origin
they have a
high uh dot product and if they are
orthogonal
so there is kind of a 90 degree angle
then then they are
as as dissimilar as possible because the
dot product will be
zero so that's the idea so now what we
need to define is we need to define this
notion of
similarity in the original network and
we need to define an
objective function that will connect
this similarity with the
embeddings and this is really what we
are going to do in this lecture
so to summarize a bit right encoder maps
nodes
to embeddings we need to define a node
similarity function
a measure of similarity in the original
network
and then the decoder right maps from the
embeddings to the similarity score
and then we can optimize the parameters
such that the
decoded similarity corresponds as
closely as possible
to the underlying definition of the
network similarity where here
we are using a very simple decoder as i
said just the dot product
so um encoder will map nodes into low
dimensional vectors
so encoder of a given node will simply
be the coordinates or the embedding of
that node
um we talked about how we are going to
define the similarity in the embedding
space in terms of the
decoder in terms of the dot product um
and as i said
uh the embeddings will be in some d
dimensional space
you can think of d you know between
let's say 64
up to about 1 000 this is usually how
how how many dimensions people choose
but of course it depends a bit on the
size of the network uh
and other factors as well um and then as
i said the similarity function specifies
how the relationship in the in the
vector space
mapped to the relationship in the uh
original uh
or in the original network and this is
what i'm trying to
show an example of uh here so
the simplest encoding approach is that
an encoder is just
an embedding lookup so what what do i
mean by this that
is that an encoded encoding of a given
node is simply
a vector of numbers and this is just a
lookup in some big matrix so what i mean
by this is that
our goal will be to learn this matrix z
whose dimensionality is d
the embedding dimension times the number
of nodes uh in the network so this means
that
for every node we will have a column
that is reserved to store the embedding
for that node and this is what we are
going to learn this is what we are going
to estimate
and then in this kind of notation you
can think of v
simply as an indicator vector that has
all zeros
except a value of one in the column
indicating
the the id of that node v and and what
this will
do pictorially is that basically you can
think of z as this matrix
that has one column per node um and the
column
store a given column stores the
embedding uh of that given node so the
size of this matrix will be
number of nodes times the embedding
dimension and people now who are for
example thinking about large graphs
may already have a question you know
won't this be a lot of parameters to
estimate because
the number of parameters in this model
is basically the number of entries
uh of this matrix and this matrix gets
very large because
the size of the matrix depends on the
number of nodes in the network so if you
want to do a network over
i know one billion nodes then the
dimensionality of this
matrix will be one billion times let's
say thousand
uh embedding dimension and that's that's
uh that's a lot of parameters so these
methods
won't necessarily be most scalable you
can scale them
let's say up to millions or a million
nodes or
something like that if you if you really
try but they will be slow because
for every node we essentially have to
estimate d parameters
basically for every node we have to
estimate its embedding embedding vector
which is described by the d numbers d
parameters d
coordinates that we have to estimate so
um but this means that
once we have estimated these embeddings
getting them is very easy is just a
lookup in this matrix where everything
is
stored so this means as i said each node
is assigned a unique
embedding vector and the goal of our
methods will be to directly optimize
or learn the embedding of each node
separately in some sense and this means
that
there are many methods that will allow
us to do this in particular we are going
to look at two methods one is called
uh deep walk and the other one is called
uh note to back
so let me let me summarize in this view
we talked about
an encoder decoder framework where we
have what we call a shallow encoder
because it's just an embedding lookup
the parameters to optimize um are
very simple it is just this embedding
matrix z
and for every node we want to identify
the embedding
z sub u and what we are going to cover
in the future lectures
is we are going to cover deep encoders
like graph neural networks
that that are a very different approach
to computing
uh node embeddings uh in terms of a
decoder
decoder for us will be something very
similar simple it will be simple
simply based on the node similarity
based uh on the dot product and our
objective function that we are going to
try to learn is to
maximize the dot product of node pairs
that are similar according to our node
similarity function so
then the question is how do we define
the similarity right i've been talking
about it but i've never
really defined it and really this is how
these methods are going to differ
between each other
is how do they define the node
similarity notion
and you could ask a lot of different
ways how how to do this right you could
say
say should two nodes have similar
embedding if they are perhaps
linked by an edge perhaps they share
many neighbors in common
perhaps they have something else in
common or they are in similar part of
the network or the
structure of the network around them uh
looks similar
and the idea that allow that that
started
all this area of learning node
embeddings was that
we are going to def to define a
similarity
um of nodes based on random works
and we are going to um optimize node
embeddings
for this random walk similarity measure
so uh
let me explain what what i mean by that
so um it is important to know that
this method is what is called
unsupervised in
or self-supervised in a way that when we
are learning the node embeddings
we are not utilizing any node labels
um we will only be basically trying to
uh learn embedding so that they capture
some notion of network similarity
but i don't need to capture the the
notion of labels of the nodes
uh and we are also not not utilizing any
node features or node attributes in a
sense that
if nodes are humans perhaps you know
their interests location
gender age would be attached to the node
so we are not using any data any
information
attached to every node or attached to
every link
and the goal here is to directly
estimate a set of coordinates
of a node so that some aspect of the
network structure
is is preserved um and in
in this sense these embeddings will be
task independent
because they are not trained on a given
prediction task
um given specific you know labelings of
the nodes or
a given specific subset of links it is
trained just given the network itself